As a magician, I'm always interested in performances that incorporate elements of illusion.
أنا مهتم دائماً بالعروض المسرحية التي تشتمل على عناصر من الخداع لكوني ساحراً.
And one of the most remarkable was the tanagra theater, which was popular in the
وكان مسرح تاناغرا أحد المسارح البارزة في هذا المجال، والذي كان مشهوراً
early part of the 20th century.
في أوائل القرن العشرين.
It used mirrors
كانت المرايا تُستخدم في هذا المسرح
to create the illusion of tiny people
لصنع خيال لأشخاص بأحجام صغيرة
performing on a miniature stage. Now, I won't use mirrors,
يؤدون أدوارهم على مسرح مصغر. إلا أنني لن أستخدم المرايا الآن،
but this is my digital tribute to the tanagra theater.
لكن هذه هي إشادتي الرقمية بمسرح تاناغرا.
So let the story begin.
فلتبدأ الحكاية إذن.
On a dark and stormy night -- really! --
في ليلة مظلمة وعاصفة -- حقاً! --
it was the 10th of July, 1856.
في ليلة العاشر من يوليو عام 1856 .
Lightning lit the sky,
و البرق يضيء السماء،
and a baby was born.
خرج طفل إلى الحياة.
His name was Nikola,
كان إسمه نيكولا،
Nikola Tesla.
نيكولا تيسلا.
Now the baby grew into a very smart guy.
كبُر الطفل و أصبح شاباً ذكياً جداً.
Let me show you.
دعوني أُريكم.
Tesla, what is 236 multiplied by 501?
تيسلا، ماهو ناتج العدد 236 مضروباً في 501 ؟
Nikola Tesla: The result is 118,236.
نيكولا تيسلا: الناتج هو 118,236.
Marco Tempest: Now Tesla's brain worked in the most extraordinary way.
كان دماغ تيسلا يعمل بأكثر الطرق غرابة.
When a word was mentioned,
عندما تُذكر كلمة،
an image of it
فإن صورة لها
instantly appeared in his mind.
تظهر فوراً في دماغه.
Tree. Chair. Girl.
شجرة. كرسي. فتاة.
They were hallucinations, which vanished
كانت تلك الصور هلوسات والتي كانت تختفي
the moment he touched them.
في اللحظة التي يمسها فيها.
Probably a form of synesthesia.
ربما أحد أشكال الحس المشترك.
But it was something
لكنه كان شيئا
he later turned to his advantage.
تحوّل لاحقاً ليكون في صالحه.
Where other scientists would play in their laboratory,
بينما كان العلماء يلعبون في مختبراتهم،
Tesla created his inventions in his mind.
كان تيسلا يُنشئ اختراعاته في مخيلته
NT: To my delight, I discovered I could visualize my inventions with the greatest facility.
نيكولا تيسلا: من أجل متعتي، اكتشفت أن بإمكاني تصوّر اختراعاتي من خلال أعظم منشأة.
MT: And when they worked in the vivid playground of his imagination,
م. ت: وحين تشتغل في الملعب الحي لمخيلته،
he would build them in his workshop.
كان يبنيها في ورشته.
NT: I needed no models, drawings or experiments.
نيكولا تيسلا: لم أكن بحاجة إلى أي نماذج أو رسومات أو تجارب.
I could picture them as real in my mind,
أستطيع تصورها في دماغي كما تبدو في الحقيقة،
and there I run it, test it and improve it.
وأقوم هناك بتشغيلها و فحصها و تحسينها.
Only then do I construct it.
وعندها فقط أصنعها.
MT: His great idea
م.ت: فكرته العظيمة
was alternating current.
كانت التيار المتردد.
But how could he convince the public that
لكن كيف يمكنه إقناع الناس بأن
the millions of volts required to make it work were safe?
ملايين الفولتات اللازمة لجعله يعمل كانت آمنة؟
To sell his idea,
ولكي يبيع فكرته،
he became a showman.
أصبح رجل عرض.
NT: We are at the dawn of a new age,
نيكولا تيسلا: نحن على أعتاب عصر جديد،
the age of electricity.
عصر الكهرباء.
I have been able, through careful invention, to
استطعت من خلال اختراع دقيق، أن
transmit, with the mere flick of a switch,
أنقل، بنقرة بسيطة على زر،
electricity across the ether.
الكهرباء عبر الأثير.
It is the magic of science.
إنه سحر العلم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Tesla has over 700 patents to his name:
يمتلك تيسلا أكثر من 700 براءة اختراع مسجلة بإسمه:
radio, wireless telegraphy,
الراديو و الإبراق اللاسلكي
remote control, robotics.
جهاز التحكم عن بعد والإنسان الآلي.
He even photographed the bones of the human body.
وقد قام أيضاً بتصوير عظام جسم الإنسان.
But the high point was the realization of a childhood dream:
لكن المرحلة الأهم كانت تحقيق حلم الطفولة:
harnessing the raging powers of Niagara Falls,
استغلال الطاقات الهائلة لشلالات نياجرا،
and bringing light to the city.
وجلب الضوء للمدينة.
But Tesla's success didn't last.
لكن نجاح تيسلا لم يستمر.
NT: I had bigger ideas.
نيكولا تيسلا: كانت لدي أفكار أكبر.
Illuminating the city was only the beginning.
إنارة المدينة كانت البداية فقط.
A world telegraphy center -- imagine news,
مركز عالمي للإبراق -- تخيلوا الأخبار،
messages, sounds, images delivered to
والرسائل والأصوات والصور تُرسل
any point in the world
إلى أي نقطة في العالم
instantly and wirelessly.
لا سلكياً و بشكل فوري.
MT: It's a great idea; it was a huge project. Expensive, too.
م.ت: إنها فكرة رائعة، كانت مشروعاً ضخماً و مكلفا أيضاً.
NT: They wouldn't give me the money.
نيكولا تيسلا: لم يرغبوا في إعطائي المال.
MT: Well, maybe you shouldn't have told them it could be used to contact other planets.
م.ت: ربما ما كان يجب عليك أن تخبرهم أنه يمكن استخدامه للتواصل مع الكواكب الأخرى.
NT: Yes, that was a big mistake.
ن.ت: صحيح، كان ذلك خطأً كبيراً.
MT: Tesla's career as an inventor never recovered.
م.ت: لم تتعافى مسيرة تيسلا المهنية كمخترع مطلقاً.
He became a recluse.
أصبح منعزلاً.
Dodged by death,
يتفاداه الموت،
he spent much of his time
كان يقضي معظم وقته
in his suite at the Waldorf-Astoria.
في جناحه بفندق والدورف-استوريا.
NT: Everything I did, I did for mankind,
نيكولا تيسلا: كل ما قمت به، قمت به من أجل الإنسانية،
for a world where there would be no humiliation of the poor by the violence of the rich,
من أجل عالم لا يتعرض فيه الفقراء للذل بسبب عنف الأغنياء،
where products of intellect, science and art
عالم تكون فيه منتجات الفكر والعلم والفن
will serve society for the betterment and beautification of life.
في خدمة المجتمع من أجل تحسين و إصلاح الحياة.
MT: Nikola Tesla died on the 7th of January, 1943.
توفي نيكولا تيسلا في السابع من يناير عام 1943.
His final resting place
و مثواه الأخير
is a golden globe that contains his ashes
هي جرة ذهبية تحفظ رماده
at the Nikola Tesla Museum in Belgrade.
في متحف نيكولا تيسلا في بلغراد.
His legacy is with us still.
إرثه لا يزال معنا.
Tesla became the man who lit the world,
أصبح تيسلا الرجل الذي أنار العالم،
but this was only the beginning.
لكن تلك كانت البداية فقط.
Tesla's insight was profound.
رؤية تيسلا كانت عميقة.
NT: Tell me, what will man do when the forests disappear,
نيكولا تيسلا: أخبروني، ماذا سيفعل الإنسان عندما تختفي الغابات،
and the coal deposits are exhausted?
وتُستنفد رواسب الفحم؟
MT: Tesla thought he had the answer.
م.ت: كان تيسلا يظن أنه يملك الجواب.
We are still asking the question.
و نحن لا نزال نطرح السؤال.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)